ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的29年後）
LAUB HILLS IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方諸國，拉歐布丘陵）
How long have you all been traveling?
芙莉蓮你們旅行多久了？
Let's see…
我想想看…
I started my journey with Mistress Frieren
我開始跟著芙莉蓮大人旅行
about four years ago.
是四年前的事情
It's been about a year for me.
我的話差不多一年吧
I see.
這樣啊
You know, this party is missing something.
話說，這個隊伍還少了點什麼吧？
Guess what it is.
你們覺得是什麼？
We have a vanguard,
我們有前衛
mages, and a priest.
魔法使跟僧侶
Perhaps a thief? After all, Mistress Frieren always falls for mimics.
也許是盜賊？畢竟芙莉蓮大人 老是會被寶箱怪給騙了
Oh goody!
好耶！
Jeez…
真是的…
Treasure chests have endless possibilities.
寶箱怪可是有無限的可能呢
You're wrong.
妳們都說錯了
You're missing something more important.
我們少了更重要的東西
It's an older lady!
是年長的大姐姐啊！
Any party has at least one!
一般隊伍裡最少都會有一個吧！
A sexy, mature lady!
那種性感成熟的大姐姐！
You think so?
是這樣嗎？
But we have Frieren.
可是我們已經有芙莉蓮了
No! I don't consider her an older lady.
不要啊！ 她才不是我要的那種大姐姐
-He looks so distraught. -Well, excuse me.
-他看起來好痛苦 -真是抱歉囉
L… Look, the next village is within sight.
看…看來下一個村莊快到了
They are breathing.
他們還有呼吸
Yeah, over here too.
對，這邊也是
What is going on? Everyone's sleeping.
怎麼回事？大家都在睡覺
This smells like trouble.
有麻煩事的氣味
Let's go to the next village.
我們去下一個村子吧
Mistress Frieren, don't make me get mad at you.
芙莉蓮大人，我會發火的喔
I was just joking.
說笑而已啦
It's a curse.
是詛咒
I knew it… What a pain.
果真是這樣，真麻煩
Hey, Frieren, what's a curse?
是說，芙莉蓮，什麼是詛咒？
Some of the spells used by monsters and demons
魔物跟魔族使用的魔法中
include ones that put people to sleep or turn them into stone.
有些魔法會讓人陷入沉睡 或把他們變成石頭
Among those spells, we refer to the ones that mankind has yet to decipher
其中人類還未能破除的部分
as "curses."
我們就稱為“詛咒”
Mankind hasn't been able to figure out how it works or how to break it.
人類至今為止還未能找出 其背後的原理，也無法解除它
So this village is beyond help?
那麼這個村子沒救了嗎？
Only in terms of "mankind's" magic.
就人類的魔法而言是沒辦法了
The Magic of the Goddess, used by priests, is another story.
但僧侶所使用的女神大人的魔法 就另當別論了
Handling curses has always been a priest's job.
解除詛咒向來 都是僧侶用來謀生的工作
How is it, Sein? Is there hope?
怎麼樣，贊恩？有希望嗎？
Don't rush me.
別急
I'm figuring out the type and source of the curse.
我正在分析詛咒的來源跟種類
How is the Magic of the Goddess different from other magic?
女神大人的魔法 跟其他魔法為什麼會不一樣？
The Magic of the Goddess is recorded in the Scriptures,
女神大人的魔法記載於《聖典》中
so only those with the Scriptures can use it.
只有持有《聖典》的人才能使用
Like the magic of demons, most of the spells
其中大多數的魔法與魔族的魔法相同
aren't fully understood.
至今還無人明白背後的原理
That's why it's not that fun.
所以一點也不有趣
Plus, it's difficult to use unless you're born with a natural gift.
而且如果沒有與生俱來的天賦 想使用的話會相當困難
That gift also makes the user less susceptible to curses.
這種天賦對於詛咒還有抵抗的作用
If I remember correctly, it's called the Blessing of the Goddess.
如果我沒記錯的話 那叫做“女神的加持”
That's why priests are generally resistant to curses.
因此，一般而言 僧侶都能夠抵抗詛咒
So even you can't defend yourself against curses, Frieren?
所以連芙莉蓮妳也無法抵抗詛咒嗎？
Mages can't detect curses that well.
畢竟魔法使無法感知到詛咒
I can somewhat sense that I am being attacked,
我或多或少有被攻擊的感覺
so I can at least tell that this village is still under the curse.
憑這點就能判斷出 這個村子依舊處於被詛咒的狀態
I feel uneasy.
我感覺癢癢的
Are you saying that we are being cursed as we speak?
妳是說，我們在說話的同時 正在遭受詛咒嗎？
How scary!
好恐怖啊！
From what I can see, it's a very unique curse.
依我看來，這是非常特殊的詛咒
You can't break the curse?
不能解除嗎？
It will require a ritual and tools.
那會需要用到儀式跟道具
It'll be faster to get rid of the source of the curse.
直接除掉詛咒的源頭會更快
The source is a monster. I know where it is already.
源頭是魔物，我已經知道牠的位置了
Let's go.
出發吧
I like that he doesn't waste time.
做事不拖泥帶水，這點我喜歡
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉蓮大人
Master Stark is…
修塔爾克大人他…
Sleeping…
睡著了
Can't you wake him up, even just temporarily?
能讓他短暫醒來一會嗎？
The spell that I can use now
我目前能用的魔法
will only keep him awake for five seconds.
只能讓他清醒五秒鐘
It won't make much of a difference.
那有醒跟沒醒一樣呢
Anyway, it looks like we don't have much time.
總之，必須加緊腳步才是上策
Fern isn't waking up. I told her we were only resting a little…
費倫起不來了 剛剛還說只休息一下子
Fern fell asleep too, huh?
費倫也睡著了啊？
We're in trouble now.
這下事情不妙了
I put up a barrier. Let's hide them here.
我設下了結界，先把他們藏在這裡吧
We're close. I can sense it nearby.
就快到了，我能感覺到就在附近
Yeah? Then wake me up when the monster appears.
是嗎？贊恩 魔物出現的時候就叫醒我吧
Don't fight it on your own.
千萬不要自己戰鬥喔
I will defeat it no matter what.
我無論如何都會打倒牠
Hey, my spell only works for five seconds…
我說啊，我的魔法 只能讓妳醒來五秒…
Frieren?
芙莉蓮？
What can you do in just five seconds?
五秒是能做些什麼啊？
Whatever…
算了
I know some offensive magic myself.
我也知道戰鬥用的魔法
A subspecies of the Chaos Flower…
是混沌花的亞種
It was using the sleeping villagers as fertilizer, huh?
把沉睡的村民當成了肥料啊？
It slowly sucks up their mana and kills them.
牠正慢慢地吸取他們的魔力 至死方休
Chaos Flowers breed with plants native to the region they're in
看樣子是 混沌花的種子與當地原生植物
to form subspecies.
繁衍出的亞種
It's almost like a mirror.
看上去幾乎跟鏡子一樣
However,
不過
no matter how much their appearance changes,
不管牠們的外表變成什麼模樣
their weak point will always be their core.
弱點永遠都在核心
Three Spears of the Goddess!
女神的三槍！
What just happened?
剛剛是怎麼回事？
Did it reflect my spell?
這傢伙把我的攻擊反射出去了？
I have to pierce through the core
我必須命中核心
or else the leaves will reflect the spell in random directions.
不然那些葉子 不知道會把魔法反射到哪些地方
It may even hit Frieren.
還有可能會擊中芙莉蓮
Damn it! This is only going to wear me out.
可惡，這樣下去也會筋疲力盡
Should I just wake Frieren up?
要乾脆把芙莉蓮叫醒嗎？
But she was a mage in the party of heroes…
但她是勇者一行人的魔法使啊
If her spell is reflected,
萬一她的魔法被反射出去
it may wipe out this forest
不只是這片森林
and even the village.
可能連村子都會被夷平
I only have five seconds. There's no time to explain.
我只有五秒鐘，根本無法解釋狀況
Plus, we haven't known each other
而且我們彼此還沒有熟到
long enough to build mutual trust and good communication between us.
能夠建立互信以及無須溝通的默契啊
First of all, I can't even tell what's going on in her mind.
最重要的是 我根本搞不清楚她在想什麼
That's right.
沒錯
I can't tell what's going on in her mind.
我完全搞不清楚她在想什麼
In my opinion,
在我的看法裡
good communication and mutual trust
無須溝通的默契以及互信
are not necessary for adventurers.
對於冒險者來說是不需要的東西
Frieren, my former comrade, was especially
特別是我以前的同伴芙莉蓮
unskilled in those areas.
對這種事情很遲鈍
So I decided to believe in her words.
所以我決定相信她說的話
She said that she would defeat the Demon King no matter what.
她說過她無論如何都會打敗魔王
And I believed those words.
我就那麼相信了
Believe her words, huh?
相信她說的話嗎？
Don't fight it on your own.
千萬不要自己戰鬥喔
I will defeat it no matter what.
我無論如何都會打倒牠
Boy, did she look dopey or what?
她當時的表情看起來還真慵懶
Don't blame me if this fails!
萬一失敗的話我可不管喔！
Awakening Spell.
甦醒的解咒
Frieren! Aim at the core…
芙莉蓮，瞄準核心…
Okay, got it.
嗯，知道了
What is going on here?
這情況是怎麼回事？
Thank you so much.
真的非常感謝各位
We are forever indebted to you.
我們絕不會忘記這份恩情的
No, it wasn't that big of a deal.
不用啦，也不是什麼多大的事
It was.
別這麼說
Thanks to you, we woke up feeling amazing.
多虧有你們 我們才能神清氣爽地醒來
The moment I woke up, I could just tell that it was
醒來的那個瞬間，我就知道了
the type that reflects magic.
那是種會反射魔法的魔物
I guess you really are an amazing mage, after all.
原來妳真的是很厲害的魔法使呢
But Sein, we were able to come out of this alive because of you.
不過這次能夠平安脫險 都是託了贊恩的福喔
Thank you.
謝謝啦
Well done.
很了不起喔
That lady from the village was so pretty…
那個村裡的大姐姐好漂亮啊…
He's still talking about that…
他又開始了…
So that's Vorig, huh?
那就是佛利希嗎？
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO,
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的29年後）
FORTRESS CITY OF VORIG IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方諸國，要塞都市佛利希）
It's a stopover on the route to Äußerst, the city of magic.
那裡是抵達魔法之都 歐伊沙斯特之前的中轉站
We're finally halfway there.
終於只剩一半的路了啊
NORTHERN LANDS ÄUSSERST - VORIG - GRANAT
（北方諸國 歐伊沙斯特–佛利希–古拉納特）
It really is a long journey, isn't it?
果然是趟漫長的旅途呢
Anyway, let's stock up on materials in Vorig and…
總之我們先在佛利希補充物資…
Um, Mistress Frieren…
那個，芙莉蓮大人…
I hate to break it to you, but we're out of funds.
雖然很難開口 可是我們已經沒有旅費了
-Hey, you there. -What?
-喂，那邊那位 -怎麼了？
That's a noble's carriage.
那是貴族的馬車
What? What do you want?
幹嘛？你們想幹嘛？
You're well-built and not bad looking either.
體格不錯，長得也上相
Come to my mansion.
你來我宅邸一趟
What is going on?
這是怎麼回事啦？
What is your name?
你叫什麼名字？
Stark.
修塔爾克
Lord Orden, we can't have you doing this.
歐爾登卿，你這樣我們很困擾的
You know who I am?
妳知道我是誰嗎？
This is the Orden Family's mansion, one of the three great families
這是北方諸國三大騎士家族
in the northern lands.
歐爾登家族的宅邸吧
Your grandfather was also very pushy.
你的祖父當年也是很蠻橫不講理呢
What kind of nonsense are you talking about?
妳莫名其妙說的什麼話？
In any case, I am speaking with Stark right now.
不管怎樣 我現在是在跟修塔爾克說話
He's the vanguard of my party.
他是我們隊伍中的前衛
Stark,
修塔爾克
do I need permission from your mommy to speak to you?
要跟你說話的話 需要你媽媽同意嗎？
Don't fight…
別吵了…
I have a request and I'm willing to pay.
我有件委託，我會付你們報酬的
This is ridiculous. Let's go, Stark.
真是荒謬，走吧，修塔爾克
Mistress Frieren…
芙莉蓮大人…
What about these copper coins?
這些銅幣怎麼了？
It's our remaining traveling funds.
我們的旅費就剩這些了
I guess it wouldn't hurt to hear you out, at least.
我想先聽聽看你的委託也無妨
Frieren…
芙莉蓮…
Stark, where did you come from?
修塔爾克，你出身自哪裡？
A village of warriors in the Klee region in the central lands.
中央諸國克萊地區的戰士之村
I see.
這樣啊
My family was originally from that village as well.
我的家族也是出自那個村子
This is my eldest son, Wirt.
這是我的長子維爾特
He is my heir and a hero of this city.
既是這座城的繼承人，也是英雄
He looks like Master Stark.
看起來跟修塔爾克大人好像
They're identical.
他們簡直一模一樣
If you brush yourself up,
只要好好打理一下
nobody other than family will notice a difference.
除非是親人，不然是看不出異樣的
Is that somehow related to your request?
這跟你的委託有什麼關係嗎？
One month ago, we had a major battle against the demons.
一個月前，我們跟魔族有過一場大戰
And Wirt died on the battlefield.
而維爾特不幸戰死了
He took down the enemy general in the process.
他跟敵方將軍同歸於盡
The silver lining is that
不幸中的萬幸是
it was a large scale, chaotic battle.
那是場大規模的混戰
The only ones who know about Wirt's death is Gabel, over there,
知道維爾特死訊的 就只有那邊的賈貝爾
and a few confidantes.
還有幾名親信
What are you planning to make Stark do?
你打算讓修塔爾克做什麼？
This Fortress City of Vorig
這座要塞都市佛利希
is this region's key defense line.
是這一帶關鍵的防守樞紐
Until we get our army back on its feet,
在恢復兵力之前
we can't weaken their morale.
不能再讓士氣遭受打擊
So you're going to hide your son's death until then?
所以你打算隱瞞死訊到那個時候？
In three months,
三個月後
there will be a social gathering with influential people from this region.
會有一場社交聚會 這一區的重要人物都會到場
There, we will show that Wirt is alive and well.
到時候必須讓大家看到 維爾特依舊好好活著
How much is the reward?
那報酬呢？
Ten Strahl gold coins.
十枚修特拉爾金幣
That'll hold us for a year with three meals a day, plus snacks.
那相當於我們一年份的三餐外加點心
Add on a grimoire.
再加一本魔導書
Take whichever one you like from the library.
書庫的藏書隨便妳挑
Wait a second! It's impossible.
等等，這根本不可能啊
What about the scar on my forehead?
我額頭上的傷疤怎麼辦？
We've already told the people
我們本來就已經對外宣稱
that Wirt is recuperating at the moment.
維爾特目前正在休養
That'll be an honorable battle scar.
那個就當作你榮耀的負傷吧
Master Stark, this is for our traveling funds.
修塔爾克大人 這都是為了我們的旅費
How depressing…
真難過…
Gabel, hammer some etiquette into Stark.
賈貝爾，給修塔爾克上點禮儀課
Master Stark, how are your etiquette lessons going?
修塔爾克大人 社交禮儀的學習還順利嗎？
It's torture.
根本是地獄啊
What do you think?
怎麼樣？
-It doesn't suit you. -How mean.
-一點都不適合你 -好過分
I'll go get some fresh air.
我去外面透透氣
Lord Orden.
歐爾登卿
Like I've said over and over again, call me "father."
我說過很多次了 你要叫我“父親大人”
You never know who is watching.
畢竟隨時都有可能被人聽見
Aren't you a little too coldhearted?
你是不是有點太過無情了？
It hasn't even been two months since your son died.
你兒子死後都還不到兩個月
I am only fulfilling my son's dying wish.
我只是在完成我兒子的遺願
We've had other body doubles.
為此我們早就準備好替身了
They didn't look as similar as you though.
但他們都沒有你那麼像就是了
I agree, it's not the best feeling ever.
這種滋味確實不怎麼好受
But this is my son's wish.
但是這是我兒子的心願
You'll have to bear with me.
你就陪我到底吧
Why can't you be more honest?
你還真是有夠笨拙
Mut, keep your back straight.
牧特，背要挺直
Yes, Father.
是的，父親
He's my second son, Mut.
他是我的次子，牧特
He is going to be my heir, and yet he's not progressing at all.
他即將成為我的繼承人 但是卻一點進步都沒有
Stark, on the other hand, is such a failure.
相較之下，修塔爾克真是個失敗品
Your posture says a lot about your swordsmanship.
你的姿勢會透露出劍技的水準
So I will teach you the Orden Family's swordsmanship.
我會把歐爾登家族的劍技傳授給你
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Don't worry. Take a deep breath.
沒關係，深呼吸一下
This isn't the village where you grew up.
這裡不是你長大的那個村子
Lord Orden, what is your opinion of Mut?
歐爾登卿，你是怎麼看待牧特的？
He's not talented like his brother.
他不像他哥哥那樣有天賦
But he's a hard worker.
但是他非常努力
The work you put into it will always pay off.
日積月累的心血不會背叛你
One day, he will become a knight that is stronger than me.
那傢伙總有一天 會成為比我還要強大的騎士
I see.
這樣啊
You should tell Mut that.
這番話你最好讓牧特知道
I always tell him.
我一直都是這麼告訴他的
That's why he gets cocky and doesn't progress.
所以他才會得意忘形，無法進步
That's a problem.
那還真是一大問題
What?
什麼？
I need to take etiquette lessons too?
我也要練習貴族的禮儀嗎？
It's a social gathering.
那可是社交聚會
Do you really think a man who is of age will go alone?
妳真以為正值適婚年齡的男性 會獨自出席嗎？
Or will his mommy escort him?
還是說他媽媽會護送他呢？
Do your best.
妳加油
This past month was absolute torture.
過去這個月根本是地獄啊
It's for our traveling funds, right?
一切都是為了旅費，對吧？
I'm sorry…
對不起…
Might as well dance, since we learned how to.
既然都這麼努力練習了 就來跳一支舞吧
It really doesn't suit you at all.
真的一點都不適合你呢
Shall we dance too?
我們也去跳嗎？
I'm eating cake.
我要吃蛋糕
Is that so…
是喔…
If it wasn't for my injury,
如果不是我受了傷
it would have been me on the frontline.
上前線作戰的就是我了
Perhaps Wirt wouldn't have died.
也許維爾特就不會戰死了
My lord…
老爺…
It seems the gathering has ended.
看來社交聚會已經結束了
You've completed my request.
你們已經完成了我的委託
Gabel, give Frieren their reward for me.
賈貝爾，替我支付報酬給芙莉蓮
Stark, you are stunningly skilled as a warrior.
修塔爾克 你作為戰士的水準可謂數一數二
If you want to…
要是你願意的話…
I can't replace your son.
我無法取代你的兒子啊
You're right…
說得也對
Just as I cannot replace your father.
如同我無法取代你的父親一樣
But you have no place to return to, do you?
但是你也沒有能回去的地方了吧？
The village of warriors in the Klee region was wiped out by demons.
克萊地區的戰士之村 已經被魔族給殲滅了
I know that much.
這點我還是知道的
My final words with my son were an argument.
我最後跟我兒子的對話是在吵架
We quarreled over something trivial.
而吵的不過是芝麻蒜皮的小事
"I don't want to see your face ever again."
“我再也不想看到你的臉了”
I just blurted that out.
我當時那樣吼了他
I didn't even mean those words.
明明也不是有心的
When I found you, I thought it was a miracle.
找到你的時候 我還以為是出現奇蹟了
Well then, even more so, I can't stay here.
這樣的話，我更不能待在這裡了
I also said something that I didn't mean
我也對撫養我長大的人
to my foster parent.
說了不該說的無心之言
That's why
正因如此
I have to bring him back lots of stories from my adventures.
我要帶很多冒險的有趣故事 回去給他聽
I see.
這樣啊
Which grimoire should I choose for our reward?
該挑哪本魔導書當報酬呢？
Mistress Frieren, it's already been half a day.
芙莉蓮大人，您已經挑了半天了
You're troubling Master Gabel.
您在給賈貝爾大人添麻煩
Hurry up…
麻煩快一點…
Look, he looks completely lifeless.
您看，人家都臉色發白了
Seems like it will take much more time to rebuild their army.
看來要重整兵力還需要很長一段時間
What's wrong?
怎麼了嗎？
Nothing…
沒什麼…
At least they won't
至少他們
have any issue with finding an heir.
不會有繼承人方面的問題了
-A forgotten hero, huh? -I don't know the name.
-被遺忘的英雄嗎？ -名字沒有人知道
-A forgotten hero. -You must've been lonely.
-被遺忘的英雄 -一定很孤獨吧
Humans mature so fast.
人類的成長還真快啊
"Long-lived Friends."
《長壽朋友》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻